Welcome back to our continued exploits with Tokenizers.
토큰이들과의 활약에 돌아오신 걸 환영해요
What we're now going to look at is what's called the instruct variance of models.
지금 볼 것은 모델 지시 변수라는 건데요
So there are many models that have been fine tuned to be specifically designed for chats, for carrying
채팅용으로 특별히 설계된 모델도 많습니다 사용자와의 채팅을 수행하기 위해서죠
out chat conversations with users, as one does with the with, uh, GPT four with with chat GPT um,
GPT4 채팅도 마찬가지입니다 얼굴을 끌어안는 모델이 등장할 경우 베이스 모델과
typically when you see those models in hugging face, you'll see that they have the same name as their
이름이 같지만 끝에 지시 사항이 추가됩니다 이
base models, but with instruct added to the end of it, meaning that they have been fine tuned to be
지시 사항 사용 사례에 적절하게 사용되도록 설계됐다는 뜻이죠
Uh, they have been trained to expect prompts in a particular structure with a particular set of special
특정 구조에서 특정 토큰으로 시스템 메시지와
tokens that identifies the system message, the user message and assistance responses so that it forms
사용자 메시지 지원 답변을 식별해 채팅을 하도록 훈련받았죠
And that is just simply part of the way that it's been trained with enough examples.
많은 예시를 들면서 훈련된 방식의 일부일 뿐이죠
So it expects it in this format, and this is hopefully going to bring some things together for you,
이 포맷에서 기대하죠 여러분께 뭔가 제공하면 좋겠네요 이제 루프를
because it's now finally going to close the loop on something where I planted a seed some time ago about
닫을 테니까요 한참 전에 메시지 구조의 이유에 대해 시드를
the reason for this structure of messages, lists of dicts that we became very familiar with when we
심었던 거죠 독재 목록은 프론티어 모델을 할 때 아주 익숙해졌어요
So I'm going to create my tokenizer this time using the meta lemma 3.18 billion instruct variant.
이번엔 토큰라이저를 만들게요 메타 lemma 3을 이용해서요 180억 개요
So this will look familiar to you.
그러니 낯익을 거예요
This is one of those lists of dicts that we use so much with, uh, OpenAI and Claude and so on, uh,
이것은 우리가 오픈AI나 클로드에서 많이 사용하는 독촉 목록 중 하나입니다 역할과 콘텐츠를
where you specify a role and content, a role a system is for the system message and user is for the
지정하는 거죠 역할 시스템은 시스템 메시지 사용자는 사용자 메시지에요
Then the tokenizers that Huggingface provide have a special function apply chat template and it will
H깅페이스가 제공하는 토큰라이저는 특별한 기능을 수행해 채팅 템플릿을 적용하고 OpenAI
take messages in this format in the OpenAI API format, and it will convert it into the right structure
API 포맷의 이 포맷 메시지를 취합니다 올바른 구조로 전환해 이 모델이 기대하는 특정
to be used for a this particular model, the type of the prompt that this model is expecting, given
프롬프트 유형에 사용되죠 훈련된 방식에 따라 토큰라이즈 = true 함수를
the way it's been trained, if you have tokenized equals true here, um, then what we'll get back is
입력하면 일련의 숫자만 나올 뿐 무슨 일이 일어나는지 알 수
just a series of numbers and we won't know what's going on.
없어요
So I've got tokenized equals false.
토큰화 = false라고 적었죠
So what we'll get back will be the, the text version of it.
Get in get은 텍스트 버전이에요
And I'm going to print it so you can see what is the uh the what is it that this is converted into that
프린트해서 여러분이 보실 수 있도록 하겠습니다 이게 무엇으로 변환되었는가
gets pumped into the model at inference time for this particular conversation.
하는 거죠 이 특정 대화에 대한 추론 시간에 모델로 펌프질되었어요
And here it is, starts with a special token begin of text and then a header.
여기 있네요, 특별한 토큰 비긴즈 오브 텍스트와 헤더로 시작하네요
And then system the word system and then end header.
워드 시스템과 end 헤더도 있어요
And then there's some information that's shoved in there about the cutting knowledge date and today's
그리고 절단 연도와 오늘 날짜에 대한 정보도 있어요
That's that's special.
정말 특별하네요
And I think that's a llama 3.1 thing.
라마 3 같아요 하나만요
I don't remember that from previous llama families, but I could be wrong there.
이전 라마 가족들은 그런 적이 없었는데 제가 틀렸을 수도 있어요
Uh, and then, um, this here is of course, the system message that we provided here.
그리고 이건 물론 우리가 제공한 시스템 메시지예요
Uh, then there is another start header for user and header.
User와 헤더를 위한 또 다른 스타트 헤더가 있어요
And then this is the user message.
이건 사용자 메시지예요
Then there's another start header and then the word assistant and then end header because we want the
또 다른 start 헤더와 보조란 단어가 있고 end 헤더가 있어요 모델이
model to generate the assistance response.
보조 응답을 생성해야 하니까요
So this is kind of teeing up the model that what should come next right after this should be whatever
이 모델은 다음 순서로 이어집니다 이 시스템
the assistance said in response to this uh, prompt following this system instruction.
지침을 신속히 따르는 지원군에 대한 대응이죠
So I'm hoping this is an aha moment for you that you see now how you can you can have a structure like
이번 기회에 깨달으셨으면 좋겠어요 어떻게 이런 구조물을 지었는지요
this.
모델과의 대화도 그렇게 생각해야 해요
But at the end of the day, what gets pumped into the model is a prompt that looks like this with special
하지만 결국 모델에는 이런 프롬프트가 들어갑니다 특별한 토큰이 들어
tokens in the mix.
있는 프롬프트죠
And because it's been trained with that structure, with those kinds of special tokens, it knows what
그런 구조와 특별한 토큰으로 훈련했기 때문에 다음에 뭐가 필요한지
needs to come next.
알아요
The assistance reply.
지원팀 응답요
So that explains the chat interfaces.
채팅 인터페이스를 설명하는 거죠
Let's work with a few more models to get some more experience with this.
get it의 경험을 쌓기 위해 모델 몇 명과 더 일해 보죠
I'm going to pick three models in particular.
전 특별히 세 가지 모델을 고를 거예요
Phi three is a model from Microsoft.
파이 3은 마이크로소프트 모델이에요
Quinn two is this powerhouse model I keep mentioning from Alibaba Cloud.
퀸 2는 알리바바 클라우드에서 계속 언급했던 강력한 모델이에요
Star coder two is a model designed for generating code.
스타 코더 2는 코드 생성을 위해 설계된 모델이죠
It's built by three companies working together, collaborating ServiceNow and hugging face themselves
세 회사가 협력해서 만든 회사로 서비스나우와 포옹하는
hugging face and Nvidia uh, that those uh, three mighty companies have partnered to make this, uh,
얼굴 그리고 엔비디아입니다 이 세 회사가 파트너십을 맺어
group star coder and have built this, uh, this particular model.
그룹스타 코더와 이 모델을 만들었죠
Okay.
네
So, uh, let's give a try for Phi three.
그럼 피3을 불러 볼까요?
So we use exactly the same approach auto tokenizer from pre-trained and we provide the model.
오토 토큰라이저와 똑같은 접근법을 사용합니다 미리 훈련받은 모델이죠
And now um I'm giving the same text.
지금은 저도 같은 문자를 보내고 있어요
I'm excited to show Tokenizers in action to my LLM engineers.
LLM 엔지니어들에게 토큰라이저의 작동을 보여 줄 생각에 신나요
I'm going to reprint the previous the llama 3.1 Tokenizers results to remind you what it's tokens look
라마 3을 재인쇄할 거예요 토큰라이저 1개 토큰의 모습을 다시 보여드리죠
Then an empty line, and then I'm going to print Phi three.
빈 선이 하나 있고 피3을 프린트할 거예요
And the question is going to be at the end of the day, do they basically produce the same tokens or
결국 중요한 질문은 이겁니다 기본적으로 같은 토큰을 생산하나요? 아니면
is it different.
다른가요?
Let's have a look.
한번 보죠
Well you'll see right away they are completely different.
보면 아시겠지만 완전히 달라요
Uh they're different.
달라요
Not only is the generated text different, but this first one, which is the start of of message special
생성된 텍스트만 다른 게 아니라 메시지 특별 토큰의 시작인 이 첫 번째
token is completely different.
것도 완전히 달라요
Uh, let's do batch decode so we can see that.
그걸 볼 수 있게 배치 디코딩을 하죠
Tokenizer.
토큰자이예요
Dot Batch decode.
닷 배치 해독법이에요
I'll have to say tokens.
토큰이라고 해야겠네요
Equals.
동등하게요
Tokens.
토큰요
Let's see what we get here.
get in the right 한번 볼까요?
Uh, and we do get something completely different.
Get in get은 완전히 달라요
And actually, interestingly, I was wrong with what I said a second ago.
사실, 흥미롭게도 조금 전에 한 말은 틀렸어요
There isn't a start of sentence special token in the case of 53, so it just goes straight into it.
53번의 경우 문장 시작 특별 토큰이 없어요 그냥 바로 들어가죠
So that's that's a very different approach.
아주 색다른 접근법이죠
All right.
좋아요
Let's use the apply chat template to see how 53 uses chat templates.
채팅 템플릿 적용을 이용해 53명이 채팅 템플릿을 어떻게 사용하는지 보죠
Let's start by doing it for llama again.
라마를 위해 다시 해 보죠
So we'll see llamas one.
라마도 볼 수 있겠네요
And then we'll print side by side the same the chat template for that same conversation, that same
그런 다음 나란히 같은 채팅 템플릿을 출력할 겁니다 같은 대화, 같은 53에 대한 같은
prompt for 53.
프롬프트를 위해서요
Let's see how they look.
어떤지 보죠
So this is the one we just looked at for for Lama, here is the equivalent for Phi three.
이게 라마에게 필요한 거고 이건 피3에 해당하는 거예요
It's obviously much shorter.
훨씬 짧죠
It doesn't pass in the the date.
날짜에 안 들어가요
And interestingly, whereas the structure for Lama was about a header and then the word system and end
흥미롭게도 라마라는 단어는 헤더가 기본이었어요 워드 시스템과 엔드
header and a header the word user and an end header.
헤더가 사용자와 엔드 헤더로 이어졌죠
In the case of Phi three there's just a special tag for system and a special tag for user and a special
파이 3의 경우 시스템을 위한 특별한 태그와 사용자를 위한 특별한 태그 보조를 위한 특별한
tag for assistant.
태그가 있어요
So it's this whole sort of different approach.
접근 방식이 완전히 달라요
Um, and that's really interesting to see that these two tokenizers, these two models just have a different
흥미로운 점은 두 토큰라이저, 두 모델이 프롬프트를 get으로 보내는 방법에
approach for how prompts get sent in.
다른 접근법을 취한다는 거죠
So obviously, hopefully you're getting the impression if you use the wrong tokenizer for the wrong
만약 잘못된 토큰라이저를 잘못된 모델로 사용한다면 가비지가
model, you'd get garbage, because obviously this with different tokens and different structure is
된다는 것을 아셔야 합니다. 왜냐하면 토큰이 다르고 구조가 다르다면 llama3에는
going to be meaningless to llama three.
의미가 없기 때문이죠.
And now let's do the same for Quinn two.
이제 퀸 2호도 똑같이 해 보죠
We're going to see the original Lama version.
라마의 원조 버전을 볼 거예요
And then we're going to show the Phi three version and then the two version.
파이3 버전을 보여드리고 두 가지 버전을 보여드릴게요
Here they come.
저기 오네요
Uh, obviously you can see totally different results for the three tokenizers.
보시다시피 토큰라이저 세 개는 완전히 다른 결과를 볼 수 있죠
Uh, and one more time highlights.
하이라이트 한 번 더 할게요
You got to pick the right tokenizer for the right model.
모델에 맞는 토큰라이저를 골라야 해요
Uh, and, uh, let's just apply the chat template and we'll see again the chat templates for that same
채팅 템플릿을 적용해 보죠 같은 메시지를 전달하는 채팅 템플릿이
message about telling a joke.
또 있어요
We'll see that for llama.
곧 알게 되겠죠
And then for five three and then for Quinn two all side by side.
다섯, 셋, 퀸, 둘 이렇게 나란히요
Let's see what they look like.
어떻게 생겼는지 보죠
We already saw the one from llama.
라마 사진은 이미 봤어요
We already saw the one from 53.
53편은 이미 봤어요
And here is the one for Quinn two.
그리고 이건 퀸의 두 번째예요
And what you'll see is that it's it's sort of somewhere in between.
보시면 알겠지만 그 중간쯤에 있어요
It does a bit like llama.
비트도 라마랑 비슷해요
It's got the, the Im start im end and system in here.
시작과 끝이라는 시스템도 있고요
Um and then user and then assistant.
그 다음은 사용자, 그 다음은 조수죠
So it's some somewhere in between the two.
그 둘 사이의 어디쯤이죠
Uh, it doesn't uh, it doesn't have something in between the word.
그 어정쩡한 단어가 없어요
It doesn't have a header special tag.
헤더 스페셜 태그가 없어요
It just has, uh, this approach here.
이런 식으로 접근해요
So it's an interesting again a third approach, another variation and with different special tokens.
흥미로운 제3의 접근법이죠 또 다른 변종으로 특별한 토큰을 사용해요
All right.
좋아요
And finally let me show you Star Coder two.
마지막으로 스타 코더 2를 보여드릴게요
This is the code generation module.
코드 생성 모듈이에요
We're going to take its tokenizer.
토큰라이저를 가져갈 거예요
And we're going to put this code in there.
이 코드를 저기에 Put 할게요
Hello world a def hello world uh taking a person variable.
안녕 세계, 안녕 세계 변수를 선택하는 거죠
And it's going to print hello.
그러면 hello를 출력하죠
And then the person.
그리고 그 사람도요
And then we just use the same encode to turn it into tokens.
그런 다음 같은 인코드를 사용해 토큰으로 바꾸죠
And what I'm then going to do is just print out each token followed by what did that get to uh, get
이제 해야 할 일은 각각의 토큰을 프린트하는 것입니다. 그리고 무엇이 get이 되었는지, 어떤 텍스트를
mapped to what what text did that represent?
나타내는지 매핑하는 것이죠.
And what you'll see here is that there was something at the beginning, and then there's def went into
여기 보시면 처음에 뭔가 있었어요 데프가 토큰 하나에 들어갔고
one token and then hello underscore world and then person.
hello_ world와 Person이 나왔죠
This here obviously will will reflect the tab and then print hello comma person close brackets.
여기 이건 탭을 반영할 겁니다 그런 다음 hello, 사람 괄호 닫기를 인쇄하죠
So it gives you some sense that, um, the star coder two tokenizer is a tokenizer that is designed
대충 감이 오실 겁니다 스타 코더 2 토큰라이저는 토큰라이저로 영어보다는 토큰라이저
around tokenizing code rather than English.
코드를 중심으로 디자인됐죠
And there's some experiments you can do.
실험할 수 있는 게 있어요
First of all, try out different tokenizers try exploring mapping from text to tokens.
먼저, 다양한 토큰라이저를 사용해보고 텍스트에서 토큰으로의 매핑을 탐색해보세요
Find out which words.
어떤 단어인지 찾아봐요
Try and find the rarest possible word that has a single token in in llamas.
라마 안에 토큰이 하나 있는 가장 희귀한 단어를 찾아보세요
Uh, tokenizer or perhaps the longest word or something like that.
토큰이거나 가장 긴 단어였을 거예요
Do some experiments, um, and then satisfy you.
실험도 좀 하고 여러분을 만족시켜 드릴게요
Satisfy yourself that if you take a pretty complicated piece of code, you should find that star coder
꽤 복잡한 코드를 가지고 있다면 이 스타 코더의 토큰라이저 토큰화가
tos tokenizer tokenizes it in a more efficient way than one of the tokenizers that's designed for just
더 효율적으로 이루어질 것입니다 토큰라이저의 영어 버전보다 더 효율적이죠
And at that point, you will be an expert in the world of open source tokenizers and you'll be ready
그때쯤이면 여러분은 오픈 소스 토큰라이저의 전문가가 되어 다음 단계인 모델에
to take on the next piece, which is models.
도전할 준비가 될 거예요
First, let's go back to the slides.
먼저 슬라이드로 돌아가죠